Hey everyone, this is Kevin from Data School.
Today you're going to learn my top 25 pandas
tricks.
These are the best tricks I've learned from
5 years of teaching pandas.
These tricks will help you to work faster, write better
code, and impress your friends.
Here's everything you're going to learn.
There's also a bonus at the end of this video
that you're not going to want to miss!
Before we start, I'm going to import pandas
and NumPy.
I'm also going to read in some datasets that
we'll be using as examples.
I'll be moving quickly, but you can download
this notebook from the link in the description
below if you want to follow along.
Let's get going!
Trick number 1.
Show installed versions.
Sometimes you need to know the pandas version
you're using, especially when reading the
pandas documentation.
You can show the pandas version by typing
pd dot underscore underscore version underscore
underscore.
But if you also need to know the versions
of pandas' dependencies, you can use the show_versions
function.
You can see the versions of Python, pandas,
NumPy, matplotlib, and more.
Thanks to Harvey Summers for this trick.
Trick number 2.
Create an example DataFrame.
Let's say that you want to demonstrate some
pandas code.
You need an example DataFrame to work with.
There are many ways to do this, but my favorite
way is to pass a dictionary to the DataFrame
constructor, in which the dictionary keys
are the column names and the dictionary values
are lists of column values.
Now if you need a much larger DataFrame, the
above method will require way too much typing.
In that case, you can use NumPy's random.rand
function, tell it the number of rows and columns,
and pass that to the DataFrame constructor.
That's pretty good, but if you also want non-numeric
column names, you can coerce a string of letters
to a list and then pass that list to the columns
parameter.
As you might guess, your string will need
to have the same number of characters as there
are columns.
Trick number 3.
Rename columns.
Let's take a look at the example DataFrame
we created in the last trick.
I prefer to use dot notation to select pandas
columns, but that won't work since the column
names have spaces.
Let's fix this.
The most flexible method for renaming columns
is the rename method.
You pass it a dictionary in which the keys
are the old names and the values are the new
names, and you also specify the axis.
The best thing about this method is that you
can use it to rename any number of columns,
whether it be just one column or all columns.
Now if you're going to rename all of the columns
at once, a simpler method is just to overwrite
the columns attribute of the DataFrame.
Now if the only thing you're doing is replacing
spaces with underscores, an even better method
is to use the str.replace method, since you
don't have to type out all of the column names.
All three of these methods have the same result,
which is to rename the columns so that they
don't have any spaces.
Finally, if you just need to add a prefix
or suffix to all of your column names, you
can use the add_prefix method or the add_suffix
method.
Trick number 4.
Reverse row order.
Let's take a look at the drinks DataFrame.
This is a dataset of average alcohol consumption
by country.
What if you wanted to reverse the order of
the rows?
The most straightforward method is to use
the loc accessor and pass it colon colon negative
one, which is the same slicing notation used
to reverse a Python list.
What if you also wanted to reset the index
so that it starts at zero?
You would use the reset_index method and tell
it to drop the old index entirely.
As you can see, the rows are in reverse order
but the index has been reset to the default
integer index.
Trick number 5.
Reverse column order.
Similar to the previous trick, you can also
use loc to reverse the left-to-right order
of your columns.
The colon before the comma means "select all
rows", and the colon colon negative one after
the comma means "reverse the columns", which
is why "country" is now on the right side.
Trick number 6.
Select columns by data type.
Here are the data types of the drinks DataFrame.
Let's say you need to select only the numeric
columns.
You can use the select_dtypes method.
This includes both int and float columns.
You could also use this method to select just
the object columns.
You can tell it to include multiple data types
by passing a list.
You can also tell it to exclude certain data
types.
Thanks to Vikram Lucky for this trick.
Trick number 7.
Convert strings to numbers.
Let's create another example DataFrame.
These numbers are actually stored as strings,
which results in object columns.
In order to do mathematical operations on
these columns, we need to convert the data
types to numeric.
You can use the astype method on the first
two columns.
However, this would have resulted in an error
if you tried to use it on the third column,
because that column contains a dash to represent
zero and pandas doesn't understand how to
handle it.
Instead, you can use the to_numeric function
on the third column and tell it to convert
any invalid input into NaN values.
If you know that the NaN values actually represent
zeros, you can fill them with zeros using
the fillna method.
Finally, you can apply this function to the
entire DataFrame all at once by using the
apply method.
This one line of code accomplishes our goal,
because all of the data types have now been
converted to float.
Thanks to Chris Moffitt for this trick.
Trick number 8.
Reduce DataFrame size.
pandas DataFrames are designed to fit into
memory, and so sometimes you need to reduce
the DataFrame size in order to work with it
on your system.
Here's the size of the drinks DataFrame.
You can see that it currently uses 30.4 KB.
If you're having performance problems with
your DataFrame, or you can't even read it
into memory, there are two easy steps you
can take during the file reading process to
reduce the DataFrame size.
The first step is to only read in the columns
that you actually need, which we specify with
the "usecols" parameter.
By only reading in these two columns, we've
reduced the DataFrame size to 13.6 KB.
The second step is to convert any object columns
containing categorical data to the category
data type, which we specify with the dtype
parameter.
By reading in the continent column as the
category data type, we've further reduced
the DataFrame size to 2.3 KB.
Keep in mind that the category data type will
only reduce memory usage if you have a small
number of categories relative to the number
of rows.
Trick number 9.
Build a DataFrame from multiple files row-wise.
Let's say that your dataset is spread across
multiple files, but you want to read the dataset
into a single DataFrame.
For example, I have a small dataset of stock
data in which each CSV file only includes
a single day.
Here's the first day.
Here's the second day.
And here's the third day.
You could read each CSV file into its own
DataFrame, combine them together, and then
delete the original DataFrames, but that would
be memory inefficient and require a lot of
code.
A better solution is to use the built-in glob
module.
You can pass a pattern to glob, including
wildcard characters, and it will return a
list of all files that match that pattern.
In this case, glob is looking in the "data"
subdirectory for all CSV files that start
with the word "stocks".
glob returns filenames in an arbitrary order,
which is why we sorted the list using Python's
built-in sorted function.
We can then use a generator expression to
read each of the files using read_csv and
pass the results to the concat function, which
will concatenate the rows into a single DataFrame.
Unfortunately, there are now duplicate values
in the index.
To avoid that, we can tell the concat function
to ignore the index and instead use the default
integer index.
Thanks to Dinesh Nair and Davis Vickers for
this trick.
Trick number 10.
Build a DataFrame from multiple files column-wise.
The previous trick is useful when each file
contains rows from your dataset.
But what if each file instead contains columns
from your dataset?
Here's an example in which the drinks dataset
has been split into two CSV files, and each
file contains three columns.
Similar to the previous trick, we'll start
by using glob.
And this time, we'll tell the concat function
to concatenate along the columns axis.
Now our DataFrame has all six columns.
Trick number 11.
Create a DataFrame from the clipboard.
Let's say that you have some data stored in
an Excel spreadsheet or a Google Sheet, and
you want to get it into a DataFrame as quickly
as possible.
Just select the data and copy it to the clipboard.
Then, you can use the read_clipboard function
to read it into a DataFrame.
Just like the read_csv function, read_clipboard
automatically detects the correct data type
for each column.
Let's copy one other dataset to the clipboard.
Amazingly, pandas has even identified the
first column as the index.
Keep in mind that if you want your work to
be reproducible in the future, read_clipboard
is not the recommended approach.
Thanks to Priyaranjan Mohanty for this trick.
Trick number 12.
Split a DataFrame into two random subsets.
Let's say that you want to split a DataFrame
into two parts, randomly assigning 75% of
the rows to one DataFrame and the other 25%
to a second DataFrame.
For example, we have a DataFrame of movie
ratings with 979 rows.
We can use the sample method to randomly select
75% of the rows and assign them to the "movies_1"
DataFrame.
Then we can use the drop method to drop all
rows that are in "movies_1" and assign the
remaining rows to "movies_2".
You can see that the total number of rows
is correct.
And you can see from the index that every
movie is in either "movies_1" or "movies_2".
Keep in mind that this approach will not work
if your index values are not unique.
Trick number 13.
Filter a DataFrame by multiple categories.
Let's take a look at the movies DataFrame.
One of the columns is genre.
If we wanted to filter the DataFrame to only
show movies with the genre Action or Drama
or Western, we could use multiple conditions
separated by the "or" operator.
However, you can actually rewrite this code
more clearly by using the isin method and
passing it a list of genres.
And if you want to reverse this filter, so
that you are excluding rather than including
those three genres, you can put a tilde in
front of the condition.
This works because tilde is the "not" operator
in Python.
Trick number 14.
Filter a DataFrame by largest categories.
Let's say that you needed to filter the movies
DataFrame by genre, but only include the 3
largest genres.
We'll start by taking the value_counts of
genre and saving it as a Series called counts.
The Series method nlargest makes it easy to
select the 3 largest values in this Series.
And all we actually need from this Series
is the index.
Finally, we can pass the index object to isin,
and it will be treated like a list of genres.
Thus, only Drama and Comedy and Action movies
remain in the DataFrame.
Trick number 15.
Handle missing values.
Let's look at a dataset of UFO sightings.
You'll notice that some of the values are
missing.
To find out how many values are missing in
each column, you can use the isna method and
then take the sum.
isna generated a DataFrame of True and False
values, and sum converted all of the True
values to 1 and added them up.
Similarly, you can find out the percentage
of values that are missing by taking the mean
of isna.
If you want to drop the columns that have
any missing values, you can use the dropna
method.
Or if you want to drop columns in which more
than 10% of the values are missing, you can
set a threshold for dropna.
len of ufo returns the total number of rows,
and then we multiply that by 0.9 to tell pandas
to only keep columns in which at least 90%
of the values are not missing.
Thanks to Ratan Rohith and Joanes Madinabeitia
for this trick.
Trick number 16.
Split a string into multiple columns.
Let's create another example DataFrame.
What if we wanted to split the "name" column
into three separate columns, for first, middle,
and last name?
We would use the str.split method and tell
it to split on a space character and expand
the results into a DataFrame.
These three columns can actually be saved
to the original DataFrame in a single assignment
statement.
What if we wanted to split a string, but only
keep one of the resulting columns?
For example, let's split the location column
on "comma space".
If we only cared about saving the city name
in column 0, we can just select that column
and save it to the DataFrame.
Thanks to Daniel Kim and Emmanuel Ameisen
for this trick.
Trick number 17.
Expand a Series of lists into a DataFrame.
Let's create another example DataFrame.
There are two columns, and the second column
contains regular Python lists of integers.
If we wanted to expand the second column into
its own DataFrame, we can use the apply method
on that column and pass it the Series constructor.
And by using the concat function, you can
combine the original DataFrame with the new
DataFrame.
Trick number 18.
Aggregate by multiple functions.
Let's look at a DataFrame of orders from the
Chipotle restaurant chain.
Each order has an order_id and consists of
one or more rows.
To figure out the total price of an order,
you sum the item_price for that order_id.
For example, here's the total price of order
number 1.
If you wanted to calculate the total price
of every order, you would groupby order_id
and then take the sum of item_price for each
group.
However, you're not actually limited to aggregating
by a single function such as sum.
To aggregate by multiple functions, you use
the agg method and pass it a list of functions
such as sum and count.
That gives us the total price of each order
as well as the number of items in each order.
Trick number 19.
Combine the output of an aggregation with
a DataFrame.
Let's take another look at the orders DataFrame.
What if we wanted to create a new column listing
the total price of each order?
Recall that we calculated the total price
using the sum method.
sum is an aggregation function, which means
that it returns a reduced version of the input
data.
In other words, the output of the sum function
is smaller than the input to the function.
The solution is to use the transform method,
which performs the same calculation but returns
output data that is the same shape as the
input data.
We'll store the results in a new DataFrame
column called total_price.
As you can see, the total price of each order
is now listed on every single line.
That makes it easy to calculate the percentage
of the total order price that each line represents.
Thanks to Chris Moffitt for this trick.
Trick number 20.
Select a slice of rows and columns.
Let's take a look at another dataset.
This is the famous Titanic dataset, which
shows information about passengers on the
Titanic and whether or not they survived.
If you wanted a numerical summary of the dataset,
you would use the describe method.
However, the resulting DataFrame might be
displaying more information than you need.
If you wanted to filter it to only show the
"five-number summary", you can use the loc
accessor and pass it a slice of the "min"
through the "max" row labels.
And if you're not interested in all of the
columns, you can also pass it a slice of column
labels.
Thanks to Alexandru Mircea for this trick.
Trick number 21.
Reshape a MultiIndexed Series.
The Titanic dataset has a "Survived" column
made up of ones and zeros, so you can calculate
the overall survival rate by taking a mean
of that column.
If you wanted to calculate the survival rate
by a single category such as "Sex", you would
use a groupby.
And if you wanted to calculate the survival
rate across two different categories at once,
you would groupby both of those categories.
This shows the survival rate for every combination
of Sex and Passenger Class.
It's stored as a MultiIndexed Series, meaning
that it has multiple index levels to the left
of the actual data.
It can be hard to read and interact with data
in this format, so it's often more convenient
to reshape a MultiIndexed Series into a DataFrame
by using the unstack method.
This DataFrame contains the same exact data
as the MultiIndexed Series, except that now
you can interact with it using familiar DataFrame
methods.
Trick number 22.
Create a pivot table.
If you often create DataFrames like the one
above, you might find it more convenient to
use the pivot_table method instead.
With a pivot table, you directly specify the
index, the columns, the values, and the aggregation
function.
An added benefit of a pivot table is that
you can easily add row and column totals by
setting margins=True.
This shows the overall survival rate as well
as the survival rate by Sex and Passenger
Class.
Finally, you can create a cross-tabulation
just by changing the aggregation function
from "mean" to "count".
This shows the number of records that appear
in each combination of categories.
Trick number 23.
Convert continuous data into categorical data.
Let's take a look at the Age column from the
Titanic dataset.
It's currently continuous data, but what if
you wanted to convert it into categorical
data?
One solution would be to label the age ranges,
such as "child", "young adult", and "adult".
The best way to do this is by using the cut
function.
This assigned each value to a bin with a label.
Ages 0 to 18 were assigned the label "child",
ages 18 to 25 were assigned the label "young
adult", and ages 25 to 99 were assigned the
label "adult".
Notice that the data type is now "category",
and the categories are automatically ordered.
Thanks to Rafi Islam for this trick.
Trick number 24.
Change display options.
Let's take another look at the Titanic dataset.
Notice that the Age column has 1 decimal place
and the Fare column has 4 decimal places.
What if you wanted to standardize the display
to use 2 decimal places?
You can use the set_option function.
The first argument is the name of the option,
and the second argument is a Python format
string.
You can see that Age and Fare are now using
2 decimal places.
Note that this did not change the underlying
data, only the display of the data.
You can also reset any option back to its
default.
There are many more options you can specify
is a similar way.
Thanks to Jeff Hale for this trick.
Trick number 25.
Style a DataFrame.
The previous trick is useful if you want to
change the display of your entire notebook.
However, a more flexible and powerful approach
is to define the style of a particular DataFrame.
Let's return to the stocks DataFrame.
We can create a dictionary of format strings
that specifies how each column should be formatted.
And then we can pass it to the DataFrame's
style.format method.
Notice that the Date is now in month-day-year
format, the closing price has a dollar sign,
and the Volume has commas.
We can apply more styling by chaining additional
methods.
We've now hidden the index, highlighted the
minimum Close value in red, and highlighted
the maximum Close value in green.
Here's another example of DataFrame styling.
The Volume column now has a background gradient
to help you easily identify high and low values.
And here's one final example.
There's now a bar chart within the Volume
column and a caption above the DataFrame.
Note that there are many more options for
how you can style your DataFrame.
Thanks to Chris Moffitt for this trick.
Now for a bonus trick.
Profile a DataFrame.
Let's say that you've got a new dataset, and
you want to quickly explore it without too
much work.
There's a separate package called pandas-profiling
that is designed for this purpose.
First you have to install it using conda or
pip.
Once that's done, you import pandas_profiling.
Then, simply run the ProfileReport function
and pass it any DataFrame.
It returns an interactive HTML report.
The first section is an overview of the dataset
and a list of possible issues with the data.
The next section gives a summary of each column.
You can click "toggle details" for even more
information.
The third section shows a heatmap of the correlation
between columns.
And the fourth section shows the head of the
dataset.
Thanks to Siddhartha, Hamza Belhadj, and Subham
Biswas for this trick.
Alright, it's your turn.
Let me know in the comments section below
which one of these tricks you're most excited
to start using!
And if you have a favorite pandas trick that
I did not mention, also let me know in the
comments.
Thank you so much for watching and I'll see
you in the next video!